Inventory of the Aleksander Pruszynski papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksander Pruszynski papers
1917-2014
2009C30
Hoover Institution Archives
17 manuscript boxes (6.8 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, reports, personal documents, photocopies of government documents, election campaign literature, and other printed matter, relating to political conditions in Belarus and Poland. Includes photocopies of Polish secret police files.
Pruszynski, Aleksander, 1934-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials originally received in 2009 with a large increment of materials received in August of 2014 and appearing under the Incremental Materials series.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Aleksander Pruszyński is a Polish, Canadian and Belarusian journalist and collector. He was born on May 4, 1934 in Rohoźnica, in what is now Western Belarus. Pruszyński is an ethnic Pole born of an aristocratic family and holds the title of a Count. Pruszyński’s father was the famed Ksawery Pruszyński: journalist, writer and diplomat. Aleksander Pruszyński holds a triple citizenship: Polish, Belarusian and Canadian. Though his political campaigns were unsuccessful, he is well known as an electoral candidate both in Poland and Belarus. Pruszyński’s primary career focus is writing and political journalism. In the 1980s he published a Polish émigré newspaper in Toronto, “The Polish Express,” and still actively publishes articles and brochures primarily for the Toronto branch of the “Goniec,” a weekly Polish magazine.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is highly eclectic and primarily composed of materials documenting various elections, both in Poland and elsewhere. It also includes information on various campaigns and controversies, ephemera, posters, various monographs and writings by Pruszyński and others. The highlights of the collection are the documents housed in boxes 12 to 15 that speak to Pruszyński’s involvement with the Służba Bezpieczeństwa (Polish security service). The period documented is 1950s to 1980s, from Pruszyński’s work as an agent for the SB to his time as an anti-communist activist in Canada. The documents in this section are copies of the original internal documents housed at the Institute of National Remembrance in Warsaw.
Due to the wide-ranging nature of the materials, especially those that were originally contained in envelopes, the collection has been kept as recevied, in its original order. The envelopes have been rehoused into folders and ordered by date the materials were received from the collector. To facilitate ease of access a detailed description of the envelope content is provided. This is a multilanguage collection in Polish, Belarusian, Russian, Ukrainian, and English.
Belarus--Politics and government.; Elections--Belarus.
- Collected Materials, 1917-2009
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series are part of the first increment of the collection. The collected materials are mainly composed of articles, booklets, clippings, charts and maps. Documents are dated 1946-2009, and are in Polish and Belarussian.
  - Articles, 1980-2009 (Text : 1: 1)
  - Belarusian Boklets, 1917-1989 (Text : 1: 2)
  - Clippings, 1995-2009 (Text : 1: 3)
  - Maps and Chart, 1970-2000 (Text : 1: 4)
- Incremental Materials, 1948-2013
  Materials in this series are part of the second increment of the collection. The series is mainly composed of bulletins, correspondence, various campaigns and controversies, ephemera, posters, various monographs and writings by Pruszyński. Materials are dated 1946-2012, and are presented in Polish, Belarussian, Russian, Ukrainian, and English.
  - Collected Materials, 1960-2013
    Materials in this series are dated 1960-2013, and are presented in Polish and Belarussian. The series is mainly composed of bulletins, correspondence, election materials, and printed matter.
    - Bulletins, 1960-2009 (Text : 1: 5-6)
    - Bulletins, 1960-2009 (Text : 2: 1)
    - Correspondence, 1993-2012 (Text : 2: 2)
    - Correspondence - Open Letters, 2008-2013 (Text : 2: 3)
    - Pamphlets, 1992-2013 (Text : 2: 4)
    - Personal, 1986-2012 (Text : 2: 5)
    - Printed Matter, 1970-2013
      - "Arche,", 2008 (Text : 2: 6)
      - "Bój Warszawy,", 1981 (Text : 2: 7)
      - "Dzieje, Sprawy Katynia,", 1980 (Text : 2: 8)
      - Ephemera, 1994-2013 (Text : 2: 9)
      - "Górny Karabach: Wydarzenia, Fakty, Liczby,", 2005 (Text : 3: 1)
      - "Inteligencja, Solidarność, Władza,", circa 1970 (Text : 3: 2)
      - Józef Piłsudski, crica 1970 (Text : 3: 3)
      - "Judeopolonia,", 1984 (Text : 3: 4)
      - "KPN: Kulisy, Fakty, Dokumenty,", 1982 (Text : 3: 5)
      - "Którędy do dobrobytu,", 2007 (Text : 3: 6)
      - "Las Sprawiedliwych: Polacy Zamordowani przez Niemców za niesienie pomocy Żydom,", 2013 (Text : 3: 7)
      - Matusik, Janusz, circa 1980 (Text : 3: 8)
      - "Peasant International in Action,", 1998 (Text : 3: 9)
      - Poems, 1970-2005 (Text : 3: 10)
      - "Polish Holocaust in Belarus,", circa 2000 (Text : 3: 11)
      - "Polski Manifest Narodowy,", 2010-2011 (Text : 3: 12)
      - "Polskie Aspekty: Stosunków Niemiecko-Sowieckich,", circa 1980 (Text : 3: 13)
      - "Prawda,", 1981 (Text : 3: 14)
      - "Proroctwo Św. Malachiasza,", circa 1970 (Text : 3: 15)
      - Pruszyński, Aleksander, 2003-2009 (Text : 3: 16-17)
      - "Raport Polska 5 lat po Sierpniu,", 1985 (Text : 4: 1)
      - "Raport z Realizacji Najważniejszych Działań Rządu,", 2005-2007 (Text : 4: 2)
      - "Rewolucjoniści, Rewolucja, Spadkobiercy,", 1981 (Text : 4: 3)
      - "Ruch Obrony Praw,", 2007 (Text : 4: 4)
      - "Stanowiska Ligi Obrony Suwerenności,", 2009 (Text : 4: 5)
      - "Strategy for Belarus: Concept of the National Development,", 2000 (Text : 4: 6)
      - "Użyto Broni,", 1988 (Text : 4: 7)
      - "Wariacje na Temat Jaruzelskiego,", 1987 (Text : 4: 8)
      - "Warszawa czasu wojny (1939-1945),", 1986 (Text : 4: 9)
      - "Wspomnienia z pracy konspiracyjnej w Sztabach Obszaru Południowo-Wschodniego Armii Krajowej,", 1988 (Text : 4: 10)
      - "Zarys działań bojowych 27 Wołyńskiej Dywizji,", 1983 (Text : 4: 11)
      - "Zarys Dziejów Sekcji Polskiej Radia BBC,", 1995 (Text : 4: 12)
      - "Zawierzenie oraz Program Naprawy Państwa i Statut,", 2010 (Text : 4: 13)
      - "Zbrodnie UB,", 2001 (Text : 4: 14)
    - Wybory, 2004 (Text : 4: 15)
  - Envelopes, 2003-2013
    Documents in this section are highly eclectic and composed of announcements, articles, booklets, bulletins, campaign materials, clippings, conference materials, election materials, ephemera, expired passports and identification cards, memos, monographs, pamphlets, political propaganda and controversies dating from late 1940s to 2013. They also include materials on Poland’s international relations, Polish presence in the European Union, and the Solidarity movement. Due to the broad nature of the materials in this series the documents have been kept in the original order that they were received in from the collector. The original envelopes have been rehoused into folders and organized by date received.
    - May 7, 2003 (Text : 5: 1)
      Anti-European Union materials from 2003 against Poland’s membership in the Union, presented in the form of bulletins, booklets and announcements. Materials in this folder are in Polish.
    - January 20, 2004 (Text : 5: 2)
      Election materials and political controversies presented in the form of announcements, bulletins, booklets and pamphlets. Materials in this folder date from 1999-2003 and are in Polish, Belarussian and English.
    - April 9, 2004 (Text : 5: 3)
      Monograph titled, “Wielkie Księstwo Józefa Mackiewicza,” by Sławomir Andruszkiewicz. Folder also includes articles and a copy of the Polish-Lithuania treaty outlining agreement of political friendship and neighborly conduct. Materials date from 1994-2003 and are in Polish.
    - October 23, 2004 (Text : 5: 4-5)
      Mainly Belarussian articles, bulletins, campaign materials and political ephemera. Also includes booklets, email correspondence and pamphlets as well as one of Pruszyński’s Belarussian publications and an article titled, “Wykaz części majątków polskich w republice litewskiej w latach 1919-1939.” Materials are mostly from 2004 and are presented in Polish, Belarussian and English.
    - circa 2004 (Text : 5: 6-7)
      Mainly Belarussian materials comprised of articles, booklets, bulletins, conference materials, election materials, and historical journals. Materials date from 1996-2004 and are mainly in Belarussian with some Polish materials.
    - circa 2004 (Text : 6: 1)
    - November 9, 2005 (Text : 6: 2)
      Comprised of articles, anti-Iraq War propaganda, conference materials, election materials, magazines, notes, and Pruszyński’s Canadian passport. Includes monograph titled, “Bigos Polsko-Białoruski lub zaburzańskie portrety.” Materials date from 2003-2005 and are in Polish, Belarussian and Ukrainian.
    - November 14, 2006 (Text : 6: 3)
      Composed of bulletins, election materials, ephemera, newsletters, newsprint, Pruszyński’s press pass, and reports. Materials date from 1999-2006 and are in Polish and Belarussian.
    - June 23, 2007 (Text : 6: 4)
      Comprising of Polish materials such as bulletins, magazines, newspapers, quarterlies, and Solidarity materials. Includes publication titled, “Wolność słowa i odpowiedzialność za słowo. Rola mediów.” Materials dated from 1994-2007 and are in Polish.
    - July 23, 2007 (Text : 6: 5)
      Composed of articles, conference materials, and election materials. Includes monographs on the topics of Cold War, anti-Russian mentality in Ukraine and Belarus, democracy versus authoritarianism, and Polish-Jewish relations. Materials dated from 1990-2007 and are mainly in Polish, with some Belarusian and English materials.
    - July 23, 2007 (Text : 7: 1)
      Articles, conference materials, and election materials. Includes monographs on the topics of Cold War, anti-Russian mentality in Ukraine and Belarus, democracy versus authoritarianism, and Polish-Jewish relations. Mainly composed of Polish materials with some Belarusian and English materials dated 1990-2007.
    - October 3, 2007 (Text : 7: 2)
      Bulletins, email correspondence, materials on Polish-Jewish relations, newsprint, and report of the Polish American congress. Materials date from 2003-2007 and are in Polish and Belarussian.
    - December 3, 2007 (Text : 7: 3-4)
      Mainly composed of articles and Pruszyński’s writings: “Open Forum-Belarus: prospects in the XXI century,” “Polacy Żydzi kto komu co winien?” “Białoruś, droga do dobrobytu.” Materials date from 2000-2007 and are presented in Polish, Belarussian, and English.
    - December 6, 2007 (Text : 7: 5)
      Comprised of bulletins, election materials, news clippings, quarterlies, and a religious booklet. Also, includes information on the Kuropaty massacre and Poland in the European Union. Materials date from 1994-2007 and are presented in Polish and Belarussian.
    - December 6, 2007 (Text : 8: 1-2)
    - September 18, 2008 (Text : 8: 3)
      Mainly composed of conference materials, newsprint and Pruszyński’s writings, some of which have appeared in earlier folders. Materials date from 2000-2008 and are presented in Polish and Belarussian.
    - March 23, 2009 (Text : 8: 4)
      Various political materials: bulletins, ephemera, monographs and pamphlets. Mainly in Belarussian with some Polish materials from 2008-2009.
    - May 1, 2009 (Text : 8: 5)
      Composed of bulletins, correspondence, ephemera, information booklets, monographs, newsprint, and pamphlets. Materials presented in Polish, Belarussian, Russian and Ukrainian, dating from 1997-2009.
    - May 1, 2009 (Text : 9: 1-2)
    - June 24, 2009 (Text : 9: 3)
      Mainly composed of publications and articles: “20 Lat Polskiej Transformacji,” “Polacy-Żydzi, Bilans Wieków współżycia,” “Krajowy Program Reform 2005-2008,” “Przestrzeganie praw mniejszości polskiej na Litwie.” Includes election materials, magazines, quarterlies and Pruszyński’s Canadian passport. Materials are in Polish.
    - July 15, 2009 (Text : 9; 4)
      Mainly composed of publications and pamphlets: “Kobiety w różnych religiach,” “Kobieta i jej misja w Katolicyzmie,” “Kwestia Ukraińska Dzisiaj,” “Odgrzebać Prawdę Historyczną spod Gruzów zafałszowań,” “Niszczenie Polski i Kościoła Dzisiaj, ” “Wojna w 1920 roku: Przyczyny katastrofy wrześniowej, ” “Źródła współczesnego ekumenizmu i Trybalizm,” “Wypędzeń Niemców z Polski po II Wojnie Światowej nie było! Niemcy kłamią!!!” Materials are presented in Polish and are dated 1995-2009.
    - August 8, 2009 (Text : 9: 5)
      Mainly composed of election materials, newsprint, pamphlets and writings. The pamphlets and writings touch on the topics of independence of Poland from Russia and the Warsaw Uprising. Materials in this folder are from 1978-2009, and are presented in Polish.
    - August 12, 2009 (Text : 10: 1-2)
      Comprised of articles, bulletins, correspondence, an interview with Adolf Pilch, and various publications: “Kronika dni Powstania,” “Noc, Nieczaj, Zdzisław Nurkiewicz,” “Żołnierze Baszty,” “O Wyborze prezydenta Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej,” “Aktywność kobiet w życiu publicznym czyli: Bez kobiet ani rusz.” Materials in this folder are from 1990-2009, and are in Polish.
    - November 10, 2009 (Text : 10: 3-4)
      Composed of bulletins, catalogues, conference materials, newsprint, and Polish constitution booklet. Materials in this folder are from 1993-2009, and are presented in Polish, Belarussian, and Russian.
    - December 3, 2009 (Text : 10: 5)
      Comprised of bulletins and quarterlies as well as documents on European Union, Energy Law of April 1997, Judaism, Solidarity and Tadeusz Cichocki. Materials in the folder are from 1993-2009, and appear in Polish, Belarussian and Russian.
    - June 26, 2010 (Text : 11: 1)
      Comprised of political ephemera and election materials as well as writings on the Katyń massacre. Materials dated 1994-2010, in Polish and Belarussian.
    - June 3, 2011 (Text : 11: 2)
      Various materials pertaining to Donald Tusk, Jerzy Popiełuszko, music notes, newsprint, Polish presence in the European Union, Solidarity, as well as information regarding obtaining Polish citizenship. Materials are dated 2008-2011, and are presented in Polish and German.
    - October 31, 2011 (Text : 11: 3)
      Folder composed of anti-Semitism materials, bulletins, election materials, examples of voting ballots, newsprint, pamphlets, Polish partisan armies, and political parties. Materials are dated 2000-2011, and are presented in Polish.
    - January 15, 2012 (Text : 11: 4)
      Comprised of bulletins, newsletters, newsprint, magazine, and materials regarding protests. Documents in folder are dated 1988-2012, and are presented in Polish and Belarussian.
    - April 30, 2012 (Text : 11: 5)
      Folder composed of bulletins, correspondence, open letters, pamphlets, propaganda poems, and Solidarity quarterlies. Also included are materials covering the Edward “Moher” Mizikowski trial, and materials on the Polish presidential plane catastrophe of 2010. Materials date from 1946-2012, and are presented in Polish, Belarussian and Russian.
    - August 30, 2012 (Text : 12: 1)
      Consist of a copy of anti-Obama propaganda, a photocopy of a hand written memoir, pamphlets, poems, political ephemera, and religious wirings. Materials are dated 2007-2012, and presented in Polish, English and Belarussian.
    - August 13, 2013 (Text : 12: 2)
      Mainly composed of a monograph written by Mirosława Sochacka entitled “Byliśmy Falszywą Prawdą.” Folder also includes materials on Solidarity. Materials in this folder are all in Polish and are dated 2009-2013.
  - Służba Bezpieczeństwa, 1950-1985
    Scope and Contens
    Materials in this section speak to Pruszyński involvement with the Służba Bezpieczeństwa, (Polish security service.) The documents cover a period of about 35 years from the early 1950s to mid-1980s. They focus on Pruszyński’s work as an agent for the SB to his time as an anti-communist activist in Canada. Additionally, some of the documents focus on the members of the Pruszyński family. The documents are internal and have been declassified and their originals are housed at the Institute of National Remembrance in Warsaw.
    - Copies of Identification Cards, 1957, 1986 (Text : 12: 3)
    - Internal Documents - Instytut Pamięci Narodowej BU 0208/1107, O/Wa WK-9954, circa 1950 (Text : 12: 4-5)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 0330/327, O/Wa WK-9954, 1965-1968 (Text : 12: 6)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 002081/3, O/Wa WK-9954/13, circa 1950 (Text : 13: 1-5)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 002081/13, O/Wa WK-9954/13, circa 1950 (Text : 14: 1)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 443/42, O/Wa WK-9954, 1968 (Text : 14: 2)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 01251/519, O/Wa WK-9954, 1968 (Text : 14: 3)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 1638/15405, O/Wa WK-9954/13, 1968-1989 (Text : 14: 4)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 0204/233, O/Wa WK-9954/13, 1969 (Text : 14: 5)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 01136/353, O/Wa WK-9954/13, 1974-1975 (Text : 14: 6)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 0716/150, O/Wa WK-9954, 1978-1985 (Text : 14: 7)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 00334/289, O/Wa WK-9954, 1979-1983 (Text : 14: 8)
    - Internal Documents - IPN GD 003/166, O/Wa WK-9954/13, 1980 (Text : 14: 9)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 0141/3, O/Wa WK-9954, 1980-1982 (Text : 14: 10)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 2418/1, O/Wa WK-9954, 1980-1984 (Text : 15: 1)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 1357/64, O/Wa WK-9954/13, 1981 (Text : 15: 2)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 1585/14521, O/Wa WK-9954/13, 1983 (Text : 15: 3)
    - Internal Documents - IPN BU 0222/243, O/Wa WK-9954, 1985 (Text : 15: 4)
- Incremental materials received in 2015 (Boxes 16-17)